<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Works on Sauvik Biswas</title>
    <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/categories/works/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Works on Sauvik Biswas</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sauvikbiswas.com/categories/works/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Jars of Blueberry Jam</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/jars-of-blueberry-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/jars-of-blueberry-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Every week at farmer’s market&#xA;She sets her bench with jars for sale&#xA;Blueberry jam on a blue tarp&#xA;Come rain or shine or snow or hail.&#xA;&#xA;Thirty winters perfected her&#xA;Recipe—consistent, precise.&#xA;Blueberry jam sealed in her jars—&#xA;She sells them at nominal price.&#xA;&#xA;“My boy is doing well in school.&#xA;My boy has topped his class this time,”&#xA;Seventeen years ago she said&#xA;With pride that caused her eyes to shine.&#xA;&#xA;The blue-eyed boy that she once raised&#xA;With money earned from blueberry jam,&#xA;He studied well and ripened sweet;&#xA;Grew up to be a splendid man.&#xA;&#xA;“My boy is off to college now.”&#xA;She met him once he moved to town&#xA;At farmer’s market every week,&#xA;While he worked hard for hat and gown.&#xA;&#xA;Desires blossomed in his blue eyes&#xA;As visions of a prosperous place.&#xA;“I will sail and settle one day&#xA;And earn myself a name and face.”&#xA;&#xA;Greener pastures ten years ago&#xA;Lured him far from his countryside.&#xA;A gift—a phone—he sent back home—&#xA;She talked with him until it died.&#xA;&#xA;Eroding smile, corroding shoes,&#xA;Hardened palms begged for care.&#xA;Summer dried up her stream of cash.&#xA;Her blue silk robes were left threadbare.&#xA;&#xA;Crumbling plaster patterns her house&#xA;It’s skeleton held by aching joints.&#xA;That thatch of dry blueberry shrubs—&#xA;Holes in canopy disappoints.&#xA;&#xA;Six years have passed, no words were heard.&#xA;Her wishful words amidst no signs,&#xA;“My boy is a man of the world&#xA;He must be happy, must be fine.”&#xA;&#xA;Every week at farmer’s market&#xA;She sets her shop, come rain or hail.&#xA;Holes in blue tarp sure disappoints&#xA;Her weathered bench with jars for sale.&#xA;&#xA;Her prayers for a blue-eyed boy&#xA;Beyond blue oceans—lives, survives.&#xA;Blueberry jam trapped in her jars&#xA;Entraps her hopes, seals them alive.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I stumbled upon this piece in my folder. I had written it in 2021. I am not sure of the exact day or month, though. —&lt;em&gt;S.B. (17.11.2022)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-hand Nostalgia</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/second-hand-nostalgia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/second-hand-nostalgia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A writer trembles in a coat that’s too thin&#xA;On frosty platform that&amp;#39;s foggy and dim.&#xA;Flickering tungsten lamp shivers along.&#xA;A shadow wearing an overcoat long&#xA;Approaches him, “Need a cigarette?&#xA;Ten-thirty today is running quite late.”&#xA;&#xA;“Some six years ago I had called it quits&#xA;But sometimes I give in,” Writer admits.&#xA;“I am a salesman,” Shadow clarifies,&#xA;“That was not free. Had you thought otherwise?”&#xA;Writer is intrigued, asks, “What do you sell?&#xA;Is there something else to warm me as well?”&#xA;&#xA;Shadow replies, “If you insist my dear&#xA;I sell nostalgia as souvenirs—&#xA;One tele show in a box-set complete&#xA;Of nameless suburb with wide-angle streets;&#xA;One fading polaroid—discoloured greens&#xA;Of nameless old man, and one in his teens.&#xA;&#xA;“One lonely guide of this planet we’re on&#xA;Penned by solitudes of men who are gone;&#xA;One used vinyl of songs that were farmed&#xA;With feels imported from post-war Vietnam;&#xA;One worn cartridge for a console acclaimed—&#xA;Twenty-first century Metroidman game.&#xA;&#xA;“Five for the cig, and thirty for my words,”&#xA;Shadow demands. “Dear, I find it absurd! &#xA;When did one&amp;#39;s company come at a cost?”&#xA;Writer&amp;#39;s displeasure feels colder than frost,&#xA;“But I am curious. You might get paid&#xA;If you can tell me where your stuff is made.”&#xA;&#xA;“Look for a train, smoking just like you are&#xA;Bound for lost times that are obscured somewhere&#xA;Where humans have walked, where cultures have thrived,&#xA;Where living have died, yet still have survived&#xA;Earnestly packing the passions of dead&#xA;In bygone objects they wrap and embed.&#xA;&#xA;“The living, the dead—they gather ’round pyres.&#xA;Yesteryear’s tales are told by suppliers.&#xA;Memories are sorted, marked and arranged&#xA;For production. In a land that’s estranged,&#xA;Dear sir, my beloved factory lies.&#xA;Making nostalgia for modern lives.”&#xA;&#xA;Shadow concludes and then extends his arm.&#xA;Reluctant Writer puts cash on his palm,&#xA;“I don’t believe a word but I’m afraid&#xA;If I don’t pay, you might leave me for dead.&#xA;Thanks for the cigarette worth thirty-five!&#xA;I don’t think your train will ever arrive.”&#xA;&#xA;“There!” Shadow points to a fog-piercing beam&#xA;A ghostly train unfurls, smoking out steam.&#xA;An unbeknownst warmth in Writer uproars—&#xA;Unknown yearnings of unacquainted yore.&#xA;“Ride is not free—”, Shadow spells it out clear &#xA;“You must pay with your memories, my dear.”&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This poem was originally published in Unicorn Magazine (India), issue July 2021. It was accompanied by six photographs that I had captured during my travels. The editor also decided put me on the cover.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backpacking and the Journey of Personal Growth</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/backpacking-and-the-journey-of-personal-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/backpacking-and-the-journey-of-personal-growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think you can backpack in that condition,” Nitesh, my seasoned backpacker friend warned me. He was right. I was overweight and lacked even the basic stamina to climb a flight of stairs, let alone sustain a multi-day trip with a loaded backpack in the mountains. In no uncertain terms, he reminded me that if I wanted to travel with him and enjoy the trip, I had to lose some weight. I still had six months to confirm my companionship. I did not want to miss the opportunity to learn the art of backpacking from him and committed myself to getting fitter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Apathy for the Future</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/apathy-for-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/apathy-for-the-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;My troubled mind wanders—lost in a troubled state;&#xA;My peace is the apathy for future outcomes—&#xA;Apathy for the future is so hard to inculcate.&#xA;&#xA;There’s calm before the storm—I let my mind meditate.&#xA;Impending cloudburst a falling droplet welcomes.&#xA;My troubled mind wanders—lost in a troubled state.&#xA;&#xA;My heartbeat chooses to race with the pace of fate.&#xA;With each pace, more fickle, arrhythmic it becomes—&#xA;Apathy for the future is so hard to inculcate.&#xA;&#xA;The calmest of waters hides a turbulence innate.&#xA;Doubts crumbling self-esteem leave trails of bread crumbs.&#xA;My troubled mind wanders—lost in a troubled state.&#xA;&#xA;These fleeting bubbles. What if the bubbles deflate?&#xA;My troubled mind to an intoxicant succumbs—&#xA;Apathy for the future is so hard to inculcate.&#xA;&#xA;My peace is the apathy for future outcomes.&#xA;In probabilities, distributions, and sums&#xA;My troubled mind wanders—lost in a troubled state—&#xA;Apathy for the future is so hard to inculcate.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; This is my first villanelle. I like the simplicity of a villanelle&amp;rsquo;s structure and the repetitive lines which, in turn, restrict the number of lines that the poet has to elaborate the idea. —&lt;em&gt;S.B. (16.04.2021)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kids who light up the rain</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/kids-who-light-up-the-rain/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/kids-who-light-up-the-rain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Have they abandoned this parking lot?&#xA;We’ll borrow roller-platforms from those limbless beggars.&#xA;We’ll skateboard; ride and roll up the concrete&#xA;While they are too busy patting their sorrows to sleep.&#xA;Let’s choose a downhill from those we already have,&#xA;Discover trenches deeper than those we already found.&#xA;Let’s roll up against gravity and hope of escape velocity&#xA;And enjoy our time in the air.&#xA;We’ll let the sparks from the bearings light up the rain.&#xA;&#xA;Have they abandoned these bent pipes?&#xA;We’ll grip them to shatter a couple of glasses.&#xA;We’ll play golf; hit stones to dissolve them in water.&#xA;Maybe we’ll invent a brand new game—&#xA;Mine is a golf club and yours a hockey stick.&#xA;We’ll make the rules as we play; pretend we’re on TV.&#xA;Let a stone fly against gravity to pierce the clouds&#xA;And create a hole in one.&#xA;We’ll let the sparks from its passage light up the rain.&#xA;&#xA;Have they abandoned these train tracks?&#xA;We’ll press ears against the rails to figure that out.&#xA;We’ll play hopscotch—jump between the sleepers.&#xA;Maybe it’s an infinite ladder lying on the ground&#xA;To erect against the walls of this infinite trench.&#xA;Hit the rails with bent pipes—let the thunder propagate.&#xA;Let’s steal some coins from those limbless beggars&#xA;And arrange them on the rails.&#xA;We’ll let the sparks from their flattening light up the rain.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I came across the phrase &amp;ldquo;The Kids that Rain Lightning&amp;rdquo; while browsing Buckethead Pikes website. It&amp;rsquo;s also one of his uplifting tracks. The rearranged phrase &amp;ldquo;kids who light up the rain&amp;rdquo; gives a completely different feel—impoverished, abandoned, angry kids who would do anything to escape their reality. Incidentally, I kept listening to Buckethead&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Whispers Way&amp;rdquo; while revising the drafts of this poem. &lt;em&gt;—S.B. (29.10.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Watching clouds pass by after an accident</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/watching-clouds-pass-by-after-an-accident/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/watching-clouds-pass-by-after-an-accident/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;I see a white hare, it’s tuft floating there&#xA;Traversing over blues. Can I have it?&#xA;There’s a goose chased by dragon in the sky.&#xA;Oh wait! Is this season duck or rabbit?&#xA;&#xA;Fuzzy shapes they make. Of muffin. Of cake.&#xA;A bowl. Some noodles! Chopsticks! Artichoke?&#xA;Look! A perfect one—encircling the Sun.&#xA;Gods must be skilled in exhaling the smoke.&#xA;&#xA;A dark one looms there. It’s far. I’m prepared&#xA;To name any shape that comes on blue screen.&#xA;This game keeps me sane while waiting for rain&#xA;To wash all the blood and mess I am in.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The genesis of this poem can be traced back to a weekend where I did nothing but lie on my bed and watch clouds drift by through a window. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t involved in any accident in real life. &lt;em&gt;—S.B. (30.09.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bowl for Alms</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/bowl-for-alms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/bowl-for-alms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Stranger, would you fetch me please my bowl for alms.&#xA;I must have forgotten it at the edge of this world.&#xA;A repurposed soup-can someone left me as a gift&#xA;Rusted so slightly around the edges of its lip;&#xA;And a dent from a kind-hearted stranger’s kick.&#xA;&#xA;Maybe it’s filled with the kindness of men&#xA;Or perhaps with emotions discarded and stale.&#xA;Feel free to take what feels joyous and good&#xA;And leave all the undesired for me to consume.&#xA;I’ll drink any emptiness if that&amp;#39;s all it brewed.&#xA;&#xA;Forgive me oh stranger for the favour I ask.&#xA;I am but bound here by the deeds of my past,&#xA;Embedded in them are nuggets of regrets.&#xA;I cannot face those who’ve inflicted more dents&#xA;On my bowl for alms, a can at world’s edge.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I felt like I had hit a slight writer&amp;rsquo;s block. I was also bedridden with slight fever, congestion and weakness. The thought of me having left something at the edge of the world kept resurfacing in my mind. —&lt;em&gt;S.B. (14.09.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tabo</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/tabo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/tabo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Hills beyond a hill, indefinite until&#xA;Brownish landscape meets with the sky.&#xA;No sight of trees to slow down the breeze.&#xA;He gushes with laughter as this river flows by.&#xA;It all turns dry through winter&amp;#39;s cold lens. &#xA;Such is this provenance of his sentience.&#xA;&#xA;Marks on the cliffs reminds him of glyphs—&#xA;Text of this Earth gets hardened, matured.&#xA;Imprinted on lime are notes of his time&#xA;And forces of violence the Earth had endured.&#xA;His cosmos forced this dissolution intense.&#xA;Such is this provenance of impermanence.&#xA;&#xA;Sutras of life, sutras describe,&#xA;He passes them on as he himself chants&#xA;Sutras of bliss. Initiated by his&#xA;Master whose teachings he had to implant&#xA;In disciples who tirelessly rehearse.&#xA;Such is this provenance of his universe.&#xA;&#xA;The stupas behind—in there confined&#xA;Meditating masters. Three jewels preside &#xA;The souls that outlast the lives of our past.  &#xA;His old remains might still be inside&#xA;These stupas and stupas in formation.&#xA;Such is this provenance of incarnation.&#xA;&#xA;The white-dotted sky opens up wide.&#xA;A luminous path paves its Milky Way&#xA;To escape from this circle and ellipse&#xA;Of birth and death bookending decay&#xA;And of his rebirth in this confinement.&#xA;Such is this provenance of enlightenment.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Last year I stayed in Tabo Monastery for a couple of days. Every night I sat under the clear skies and wondered how the lives of the monks would have been a couple of centuries ago. This poem was a difficult one to write. I had a draft idea lying around for a number of days with no clue about how to approach it. Then, out of nowhere, the whole poem came together in a couple of hours. &lt;em&gt;—S.B. (01.09.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Don’t forget to breathe</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/dont-forget-to-breathe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/dont-forget-to-breathe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;You’ve been out for a couple of seconds&#xA;You are a slimy drip, you are still.&#xA;Someone then smacks your back&#xA;You cry and let your lungs fill.&#xA;Your first punishment in this world&#xA;First life-lesson to be instilled—&#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe”&#xA;&#xA;The city you chose to grow up in&#xA;Is obscured in smog-like stuff.&#xA;You play around but suffocate&#xA;When the air is not enough.&#xA;The corticosteroids will save you—&#xA;You hear that inhaler puff,&#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe.”&#xA;&#xA;You’ve brought on stage your nervous self&#xA;Through your songs you emote.&#xA;You navigate the highs and lows&#xA;Then hold indefinitely a note;&#xA;Claps and cheers intensify&#xA;As the voice escapes your throat,&#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe.”&#xA;&#xA;A being of beauty catches your eyes.&#xA;Your desire, for yours to keep.&#xA;A needle skipping over gramophone groves&#xA;Your heartbeat chooses to skip.&#xA;Jaws open wide, commotions drown&#xA;You sense the being speak,&#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe.”&#xA;&#xA;You may choose to detach yourself&#xA;For the You you’d wish to find.&#xA;And learn the ins and exhalations&#xA;And the rituals to unwind.&#xA;You have mastered all the patterns&#xA;But then your master reminds, &#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe.”&#xA;&#xA;Dusty chalks pollute the cracks,&#xA;You hang on with your fingers.&#xA;Slam your A-game against the cliff&#xA;And challenge Nature to bring hers.&#xA;Her stack of rocks stacked against you,&#xA;In the breeze you hear her whisper,&#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe.”&#xA;&#xA;Men had to fish your body—&#xA;Been two hours that you slipped.&#xA;No amount of pressure on your chest&#xA;Or forced air through your lips&#xA;Will make you hear or understand&#xA;The words your loved one weeps,&#xA;    “Don’t forget to breathe.”&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I wrote this poem quite rapidly—over a period of three days. The idea of what could take one&amp;rsquo;s breath away kept playing in my mind. —&lt;em&gt;S.B. (18.07.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A TV reporter stuck on page two-and-a-half</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/a-tv-reporter-stuck-on-page-two-and-a-half/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/a-tv-reporter-stuck-on-page-two-and-a-half/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;“Here comes Mr. Roy—the rising young star,&#xA;He steps out of mansion and heads for the car.&#xA;His girlfriend is with him in a stunning blue dress.&#xA;He himself in casuals is dressed to impress.&#xA;Rumour has it—they are headed for a play.&#xA;They met at a party an year ago, this day.&#xA;Will he propose? His fans want to know.&#xA;If he does, we will be the first ones to show.”&#xA;She moves her mic, “Do you have it on tape?”&#xA;Her cameraman assures, “Don’t worry. It’s safe.”&#xA;&#xA;Back in the office, her boss is annoyed,&#xA;“What are you doing? Roy is unemployed.&#xA;Two years have passed since he had his last hit.&#xA;Rich dad has saved him from hitting the streets.&#xA;His girlfriend is spoiling his money and his head.&#xA;Now go edit that story on Kabir instead?&#xA;He has a future. You will have, too,”&#xA;And points at a junior, signals her to pursue.&#xA;The junior smirks. Inside she feels dead&#xA;And silently obliges hanging her head.&#xA;&#xA;Small concrete cage, two hours to return—&#xA;All she can afford for the salary she earns.&#xA;Two hours in a crowd that’s trained to destroy&#xA;Motivation, enthusiasm and last drop of joy.&#xA;Her mom calls her up, “How was your day?”&#xA;She puts on a smile; says, “It was okay.”&#xA;Mundane exchanges, then she winds up the call,&#xA;And stares at a poster hanging on the wall.&#xA;Roy from his last hit stares through her soul.&#xA;There boss, here crush—no freedom, no parole.&#xA;&#xA;Next day arrives to shake yesterday off.&#xA;She gets off her bed and forgets she was scoffed.&#xA;She puts on her make-up; puts on a dress&#xA;To ride in a crowd to that upmarket place.&#xA;Her cameraman’s there. He hands her the mic.&#xA;They wait for their prey and a moment to strike.&#xA;As soon as he&amp;#39;s spotted with his girlfriend behind,&#xA;She fixes her hair and the state of her mind.&#xA;Her cameraman signals as he shoots from afar.&#xA;“Here comes Mr. Roy—the rising young star.”&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The topic came from a discussion with Amit Prabhakar. I told him that I can write a very short story. It became a poem instead. &lt;em&gt;—S.B (09.08.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bomberman and the Locksmith</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/the-bomberman-and-the-locksmith/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/the-bomberman-and-the-locksmith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sauvikbiswas.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/Bomberman-and-Locksmith.pdf&#34;&gt;Click here&lt;/a&gt; to download a pdf version of this play.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;cast-of-characters&#34;&gt;&#xA;  Cast of Characters&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#cast-of-characters&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SHAKYA Pahaadi&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;About 35 years old. A god-fearing, traditional pahaadi person. He is married to a pahaadi woman from a neighbouring village across a pass. He has a 12-year-old daughter whom he considers to be very intelligent. Runs a guest-house-cum-tenting facility during the peak hiking season. He farms vegetables like spinach, potatoes and carrots during good weather.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Busking Bard</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/the-busking-bard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/the-busking-bard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Halt o’ kind men, in suit, in pursuit.&#xA;Listen to the tales I sing on my lute.&#xA;When I conclude&#xA;I’ll lighten your mood&#xA;With three bars of music, and one string of truth.&#xA;&#xA;One song for sorrow and three songs of joy;&#xA;A verse on the verso—this tale is a decoy&#xA;Of turns of events.&#xA;Our hero ascents&#xA;To rectify on recto for you to enjoy.&#xA;&#xA;A tale of a trip, a stain on your shirt,&#xA;A jab of misfortune stuck like the dirt.&#xA;Spare me your hate.&#xA;I’m a mirror to reflect&#xA;Your failures in love our hero will avert.&#xA;&#xA;Humour my hero for the time he has clocked.&#xA;My tales are but woven for you to be mocked.&#xA;These songs that I play&#xA;May mock you today.&#xA;But they hide the truth of the path to be walked.&#xA;&#xA;My truth is coins that you would have tossed.&#xA;The claps and the cheers, the moments that crossed&#xA;Are fictional stripes&#xA;In tales of our lives.&#xA;Once I have left, my place would be lost.&#xA;&#xA;My songs and my tales will linger for days—&#xA;Or if sung to your kids—a couple of decades.&#xA;They’ll lose their use,&#xA;And no longer amuse;&#xA;They will erode from your consciousness.&#xA;&#xA;A hundred years later, I will come lay my claim&#xA;On songs of the miseries that you overcame.&#xA;I’ll once again narrate&#xA;The deceptions of fate.&#xA;I&amp;#39;ll have a new crowd; I&amp;#39;ll have a new name.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; I thought it would be a neat little trick to use approximately metered limerick for portraying the philosophy of a poor busker. &lt;em&gt;—S.B. (31.07.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rishikesh</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/rishikesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/rishikesh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The day they finally hid Jonathan Bakshi in a box&#xA;And lowered him behind a church that was marked orthodox,&#xA;Although he wasn’t one, that I can say&#xA;For I have known him for years, maybe months and even days.&#xA;His wife departed him—a stroke she couldn’t evade.&#xA;Behind the same orthodox church, her mortal body was laid.&#xA;Since the day he outlived her, two decades have gone&#xA;Leaving him to raise his son as a father and a mom.&#xA;His son later settled abroad and has two sons of his own—&#xA;Their faces soothed Bakshi when he saw them on the phone.&#xA;Bakshi’s pension served him well with rent to shelter him&#xA;And food to calm his stomach but not the nightmares in his dreams.&#xA;I still remember searching for meaning and a place&#xA;Six of us in seventy-six, hunting dorms in Rishikesh.&#xA;&#xA;Beside the turbulent Ganges, we engaged in debates—&#xA;Was India on the right track? Would all of us get laid?&#xA;Was Indira on the right track? Were the poor getting their due?&#xA;Was three decades of freedom not enough for a review?&#xA;Was socialism a concern? Was population a constraint?&#xA;That’s when we met a full time saint and a part time merchant.&#xA;“Would you want some of these—the finest of the fine?&#xA;You’ll never find these elsewhere—they’re one of a kind.&#xA;These dark sticks are stuffs that gods have always used&#xA;To design and build the cosmos, its bolts and its screws.&#xA;You&amp;#39;ll unlock the secrets they have hidden all around&#xA;Inside your mind, above the skies and beneath this holy ground.”&#xA;Six of us paid in cash—caught up in his praise&#xA;Of the promises of discoveries in the hash of Rishikesh.&#xA;&#xA;Banerjee’s discovery lasted for a couple of years more.&#xA;His father had enough. He was off to prosperous shores&#xA;Where he discovered more banks—unlike the ones we were on.&#xA;Rode the bulls for gourmet and ladies, big palaces with lawns.&#xA;Until the bear took everything, but dues had to be paid.&#xA;Colt finally offered him a choice—through his mouth or against his head.&#xA;That Bannerjee was still three-and-a-light years away—&#xA;He was not his upper-class self—not his father’s protege.&#xA;A red bandana for a fedora, checkered kurta instead of suit,&#xA;Pocketed hands in a thin frame, slippers instead of boots.&#xA;He wrote poetry and published op-eds in local press;&#xA;He wrote about the downtrodden, the oppressed, the distressed.&#xA;We smoked up the hash, as we heard Banerjee paraphrase&#xA;Lenin, Marx and Engels on the banks in Rishikesh.&#xA;&#xA;Banerjee felt they were poster boys of religious tolerance—&#xA;Tiwari and Ali in reality were just childhood friends.&#xA;They didn’t care much, other than the company that we fostered&#xA;And taunted Banerjee if he had painted Bakshi in his poster.&#xA;Puff in the air, every future they spoke, raised their hopes&#xA;As they planned hotels and inns, and skiing resorts up on the slopes.&#xA;They would later follow their dreams, the cash, and the hand.&#xA;They followed up with what the tourist-market would demand.&#xA;Made friends with the politicians, the administrators, and the wise.&#xA;Our part-time merchant helped them out—deals were legitimised.&#xA;Tiwari’s daughter is married to a well-known TV star.&#xA;Ali’s eldest of the three puts a red beacon on his car.&#xA;Twenty thirteen would annihilate their family and progress.&#xA;No one found their bodies. They must have washed through Rishikesh.&#xA;&#xA;“Don’t you guys feel the flow; this place where Beatles had been—&#xA;Somewhere under the Ganges, they have hid their submarine,”&#xA;Paul mumbled as he stumbled through the same chords in circles,&#xA;And climbed the stairs of Zeppelins, and smoked up Deep Purples,&#xA;And shredded Hendrix’s electric solos on a cheap acoustic guitar,&#xA;And flew amongst the colours of Gauguin, Gogh and Renoir.&#xA;“This hash is definitely stolen from the gods’ abode.&#xA;This surpasses the sunshine we have imported from abroad.”&#xA;But his body was too frail to hold the drugs and the chords,&#xA;As cancerous cells began to grow—unbounded of sorts.&#xA;Six months later, Paul threw up blood on the floor&#xA;Doctors strapped and tubed him and said, “Maybe six more.”&#xA;Paul dreamt of tangerine trees as he counted down his days&#xA;The sky would turn marmalade for him in Rishikesh.&#xA;&#xA;“Who has died?”—it’s not the right question my friend,&#xA;The act of dying is always a lonely journey in the end&#xA;How about we ask instead, “what then has died?”&#xA;Idealism, youth, utopia—philosophies side by side.&#xA;Six friends were six different individuals, too—&#xA;A ragtag group of young men with different world-views&#xA;Who in turn grew and morphed as time passed by,&#xA;And begs us to ask the question, “when do you think has died?”&#xA;Enthusiasm has dulled itself. Novelty is mundane.&#xA;What once eased our raging blood now soothes arthritic pain.&#xA;Generations will make new friends, new Rishikeshes they will find,&#xA;Their Gangeses will morph their views and flow with the times.&#xA;Bakshi, say I’ve missed them. They are not here in flesh.&#xA;Soon I’ll join to laugh with you guys—just like in Rishikesh.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; None. Nil. Nada. Zilch. Took me freaking six major drafts to write and I still feel it can be better. &lt;em&gt;—S.B. (28.05.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>You are not made of nouns</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/you-are-not-made-of-nouns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/you-are-not-made-of-nouns/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;You are not made of nouns—Not the one gifted properly when you were welcomed into this world,Not the ones of convenience by those that saw you grow up,Not the ones of ridicule for some couldn’t stand your presence,Not the ones of adoration by those who moved your essence.You are not made of nouns—Not the laid out job descriptions nor what you are asked to achieve—Not a writer or a painter; not a preacher, saint or thief,Not the roles what society calls a father, husband or son,Not the traits of your genetic makeup you had never agreed upon.You are not made of nouns—Not the ties that define your circles, your actions or your words,Not the confines of identities that identifies your herds,Not the characters you must carry from birth until your death,Not the brandings you must fend with your blood, your sweat and breath.You are not made of nouns.In a different world you would be a different set of words.Your name may be undefined and you would identify with the verbs.There may not be a language, no words to make the list;There wouldn’t be any nouns around, but you would still exist.&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; As of today, my website says that I am a &lt;em&gt;Comics geek, Musician, Programmer, Traveller and Malfunctioning Robot&lt;/em&gt;. I am guilty of this. We are all guilty of this. We give names, grant roles and associate identities to people and expect them to fulfil the meanings that these arbitrary words carry. &lt;em&gt;—S.B. (26.05.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This freedom that&#39;s bestowed on us</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/this-freedom-thats-bestowed-on-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/this-freedom-thats-bestowed-on-us/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;This freedom that&amp;#39;s bestowed on us    is not devoid of suffering.Each tie we cut exercises    our tolerance of agony.Relinquish the comforts of    mind and flesh for thoughts to let shrinkand relish the silent breathing.    Relinquish these ties to be free.Suffering of the saints, the martyrs    are cast from the same hardened mould—fights indistinguishable from    each other, as the battered remainsreminds the other of paths that    destinies might have had foretold.Both fights are but fights of freedom    fought in their own unyielding ways.A fight of the middle class and    a plight of downtrodden and poor;sufferings in lieu of comfort,    sharp blades in lieu of bouquets.Choices shroud the destined outcomes    lurking beyond translucent doorsopened their own definition    of freedom—would’ve chosen anyways!There aren&amp;#39;t leftist propagandas,    no doctrines of righteous right,no drug psychotropic enough    for truth that illusion portrays;or the temporal suspension of    reality for our delight—As we search for our own freedom    ourselves, in our own selfish ways.This freedom that&amp;#39;s bestowed on you    is not devoid of sufferingsduring your spatial–temporal     stroll through a predetermined world.Was suffering your exercise in    your mindful self-discoverywhile you and your freedom wait    for the certain future to unfurl?&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I was meditating on the idea of freedom and how discomfort and suffering is a part of achieving any form of freedom—mental, physical, or spiritual. I also found it amusing that no matter how we take the suffering, we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be drifting away from a deterministic world if that is the case. —&lt;em&gt;S.B. (16.05.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can I steal this happiness?</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/can-i-steal-this-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/can-i-steal-this-happiness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;(You) gave me these pills and then drugs, sex and bliss.Water streamed, money flowed drained out like piss.Ecstasy kicked in and I felt so scarred.Gazed on two lovers walking the boulevard—(They) looked at each other for stealing a kiss.Can I steal this happiness?(I) made myself guest for those you have called friends.Swallowed their drinks, to their wills I have bent.Offered a handshake, my eyes shot a glanceUnder the street-light where two children danced—Stomping on puddles to steal some more stains.Can I steal this happiness?(I) flew to the beaches, on shores I found spreadClam shells and fragments of molluscs long dead.Like all the bones I have stolen before—(And) waited for waves that could clean off your shores.(An) ageing man walks on and steals one more breath.Can I steal this happiness?(I) ran from my city, my house and my goods(To) footpath that winds on and drifts into woods.Counting these trunks that had hindered my view(Re)minds me of all those I’ve silenced for you.(A) blackbird steals silence from depth of those woods.Can I steal this happiness?(I) climbed over rocks and scaled boulders below(To) catch those peaks basking in dawn’s alpenglow.Just like I’ve stepped on those vanquished for you(For) want of money and acknowledgement too.(The) peaks stole the sunlight to light up the snow.Can I steal this happiness?&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; I wrote these words for one of my band&amp;rsquo;s tracks. It was never made. There are a lot of bracketed words that are supposed to be just glanced over or passed on for the next stressed syllable. The subject matter is something that I keep returning back to—if the modern society and our ways are conducive of real happiness. —&lt;em&gt;S.B. (14.04.2020)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
