<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Published on Sauvik Biswas</title>
    <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/tags/published/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Published on Sauvik Biswas</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sauvikbiswas.com/tags/published/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Second-hand Nostalgia</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/second-hand-nostalgia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/second-hand-nostalgia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A writer trembles in a coat that’s too thin&#xA;On frosty platform that&amp;#39;s foggy and dim.&#xA;Flickering tungsten lamp shivers along.&#xA;A shadow wearing an overcoat long&#xA;Approaches him, “Need a cigarette?&#xA;Ten-thirty today is running quite late.”&#xA;&#xA;“Some six years ago I had called it quits&#xA;But sometimes I give in,” Writer admits.&#xA;“I am a salesman,” Shadow clarifies,&#xA;“That was not free. Had you thought otherwise?”&#xA;Writer is intrigued, asks, “What do you sell?&#xA;Is there something else to warm me as well?”&#xA;&#xA;Shadow replies, “If you insist my dear&#xA;I sell nostalgia as souvenirs—&#xA;One tele show in a box-set complete&#xA;Of nameless suburb with wide-angle streets;&#xA;One fading polaroid—discoloured greens&#xA;Of nameless old man, and one in his teens.&#xA;&#xA;“One lonely guide of this planet we’re on&#xA;Penned by solitudes of men who are gone;&#xA;One used vinyl of songs that were farmed&#xA;With feels imported from post-war Vietnam;&#xA;One worn cartridge for a console acclaimed—&#xA;Twenty-first century Metroidman game.&#xA;&#xA;“Five for the cig, and thirty for my words,”&#xA;Shadow demands. “Dear, I find it absurd! &#xA;When did one&amp;#39;s company come at a cost?”&#xA;Writer&amp;#39;s displeasure feels colder than frost,&#xA;“But I am curious. You might get paid&#xA;If you can tell me where your stuff is made.”&#xA;&#xA;“Look for a train, smoking just like you are&#xA;Bound for lost times that are obscured somewhere&#xA;Where humans have walked, where cultures have thrived,&#xA;Where living have died, yet still have survived&#xA;Earnestly packing the passions of dead&#xA;In bygone objects they wrap and embed.&#xA;&#xA;“The living, the dead—they gather ’round pyres.&#xA;Yesteryear’s tales are told by suppliers.&#xA;Memories are sorted, marked and arranged&#xA;For production. In a land that’s estranged,&#xA;Dear sir, my beloved factory lies.&#xA;Making nostalgia for modern lives.”&#xA;&#xA;Shadow concludes and then extends his arm.&#xA;Reluctant Writer puts cash on his palm,&#xA;“I don’t believe a word but I’m afraid&#xA;If I don’t pay, you might leave me for dead.&#xA;Thanks for the cigarette worth thirty-five!&#xA;I don’t think your train will ever arrive.”&#xA;&#xA;“There!” Shadow points to a fog-piercing beam&#xA;A ghostly train unfurls, smoking out steam.&#xA;An unbeknownst warmth in Writer uproars—&#xA;Unknown yearnings of unacquainted yore.&#xA;“Ride is not free—”, Shadow spells it out clear &#xA;“You must pay with your memories, my dear.”&#xA;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Notes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This poem was originally published in Unicorn Magazine (India), issue July 2021. It was accompanied by six photographs that I had captured during my travels. The editor also decided put me on the cover.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backpacking and the Journey of Personal Growth</title>
      <link>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/backpacking-and-the-journey-of-personal-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sauvikbiswas.com/works/backpacking-and-the-journey-of-personal-growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“I don’t think you can backpack in that condition,” Nitesh, my seasoned backpacker friend warned me. He was right. I was overweight and lacked even the basic stamina to climb a flight of stairs, let alone sustain a multi-day trip with a loaded backpack in the mountains. In no uncertain terms, he reminded me that if I wanted to travel with him and enjoy the trip, I had to lose some weight. I still had six months to confirm my companionship. I did not want to miss the opportunity to learn the art of backpacking from him and committed myself to getting fitter.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
